[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host joavan proni and
today we'll be discussing ruthless
security for busy developers with
Charles Weir Charles is a developer
security researcher with with over 30
years of experience in the software
industry he's currently a research
fellow at security Lancaster where he
leads the research on how to improve the
security of software delivered by
development teams he was a technical
lead for the world's first smartphone
the Ericson
r380 and was app security lead for the
world's first Android payment app e cash
on to and he's the author of the
developer Security Essentials package a
set of workshops that help Developers
understand and apply security principles
in their work Charles welcome to
software engineering radio is there
anything I miss that you'd like to add
no except I'm a fan of software
engineering radio and I was on a very
very early podcast yeah was that one was
about small memory software perhaps that
was it okay but let's talk about
ruthless Security today yeah so can you
give us a brief overview of what
ruthless security for busy Developers is
about and why we should care well
security is hard work it's expensive it
requires a lot of effort in fact you
could allow it to take all of your time
developing and and then
some so that's clearly not going to be
practical so we all have to make choices
about what security we Implement and
what ruthless security is promoting is
making those choices is hard using hard
data to
ruthlessly avoid the things that simply
you feel might be good but doing the
right
things okay so is a way of prioritizing
risks indeed that's how we do it and
deciding which risks we want to take and
which ones we can forget about am I
correct that's correct okay I would like
also to ask when we're talking about
security we also often end up talking
about privacy and sometimes conflating
the two now this is perhaps not entirely
related to ruthless security but I think
is a distinction that I'd like to to ask
you about so can you tell us the
difference between them and how they
relate to each other well security is
usually about someone else it's about
bad things that we don't want to happen
happening through our
software it's often divided into
confidentiality integrity and
availability the
CIA and which is people don't find out
things you don't want them to do people
don't change things you don't want them
to do and people don't stop the system
working so the sorts of risks we're
talking about of financial loss physical
harm loss of service that sort of stuff
privacy is about personal information
like what we've done what our birthdays
are whatever it might be and examples of
problems might be surveillance or
accidental leaks of my personal
information to the world or somebody
deliberately sharing them where they
shouldn't go and the bad things that can
happen are fraud as a result because
somebody's got information they oughtn't
to have embarrassment which could be
very severe or people manipulating
people in different
ways and what is the relationship
between the two because I guess for
privacy a level of security can be
necessary there's a big overlap yes and
frequently people just conflate the two
but privacy is often about things that
aren't strictly speaking problems with
the software they're not bugs they were
just in the
design it wasn't quite that thing hadn't
been thought about or thought important
so privy is in a way a more subtle
one it's and you can't tackle it easily
using the the techniques we've got from
the military of of hardening and and
stopping
vulnerabilities in your security
workshops you mention three vital
ingredients you know need for software
projects and say risk assessment risk
information and development integration
can you tell us a bit more about those
ingredients why they're vital and how
they relate to secure
development so it sounds
huge in fact it's probably not this is
three things that we believe every
development should at least think
about so risk assessment is looking at
what could possibly go
wrong and thinking of how you might deal
with it How likely it is and how bad it
would be if it happened happened the
risk information is what you might need
in order to do those
calculations so it might be someone
else's previous assessment your previous
assessment even it might be industry
knowledge it might be other people
coming in and sort of advising you on
what could possibly go wrong and the
development integration is what makes
the other two happen so it's how and
when are you going to do this and again
we would recommend building it in so
that you at least spend a little time on
this I'm talking perhaps a meeting or
something at least every six months or
so but possibly more often depending on
your project and also another question
general question about security security
can be a very broad subject and when
thinking about it in the context of
software development in my experience at
least many developers seem to think
about the O top 10 or aspects around the
design and implementation of their own
systems how are we going to do
authentication authorization in these
particular apis or things like this but
not necessarily the surrounding context
so as some example I can give you things
like the environment where the software
will be used or will be run or maybe we
are installing this in the cloud saying
AWS how are we going to store the
various secrets and keys in a way that
is that is good for our security
purposes and so when talking about
secure development from your point of
view what is in scope and out of scope
my answer to that is it's all in scope
to
consider but it's certainly not going to
end up in scope to implement so so as a
software
developer we need to think about things
like what could happen what what the
hardware will be and how it all works as
a system so you've got things like
social engineering as you say often as
developers or as as a development team
including the product owner and and the
other people involved we have to say
well actually we can't do anything about
that and so you get a security you often
need to document that in some way to say
well if it happens it's not our problem
we believe it is this problem or it's
going to be an act of God because
there's nothing anybody can do about it
so one of the ways of dealing with the
security problem is to have a boundary
and say here's our here's the limit of
our concern this is what we're going to
deal with this is this is what is not
our problem it might be the purchasers
problem it might be the end users
problem it might be any other
stakeholders problem but so long as we
have defined that we have done a
responsible job I see so if I am
understanding correctly I try to say
shortly what I understand here is is
highly context dependent somehow so it's
context dependent what you will do about
it but you want to consider all possible
aspects at least at the beginning to
decide where the boundaries are in the
first place yes that's it in your secure
development site you state that good
enough security is essential for almost
every software
development now can you expand on what
you mean with good enough and how to
judge if we reach that level or
not I suppose I one might actually
phrase it the other way around and say
for some software developments good
enough security is none so I would
suggest that there's quite a number of
development so like examples of software
development where frankly you don't have
to do any security or any privacy but
it's worth having a quick think
first whether that's actually true so
examples might be you do some complex
thing on a spreadsheet to do some sort
of sophisticated analysis all right
who's going to attack that nobody's
going to know it exists who going to has
it got a privacy
implication probably not but it could do
have to just just think a little bit
depends on what's on the spreadsheet is
there any other issue probably not so so
just I would suggest of anything more
than putting together a quick script to
do something you might well want to do a
quick think have I got any
responsibilities here in security and
privacy but for quite a lot of
mundane applications the answer will be
nah not really and for the applications
in which instead security matter which
seems to be probably the majority of the
applications out there you know if we if
we exclude the I don't know the scripts
I may write to do some automation at
home or my own spreadsheets for my home
accounting stuff like this but for all
the other applications that need
security how do we decide when good
enough is enough I mean how do we decide
the level of security we want that is a
business
decision it's a management if you wanted
to study that would study it that would
be a management style study it would be
about benefits to your organization or
yourself and whether the costs are worth
it we might think about whether there
could be met tricks and this discussion
comes up whenever developer centered
researchers come together both industry
and otherwise and the answer is we don't
know of any metrics that really capture
this I've in my research I've used
metrics to see whether development teams
are improving their security as a result
of workshops or improving their thinking
about security and that is measurable
and useful but to to actually be able to
say anything useful about the outcomes
is very hard because it all becomes
involved in other business concerns and
marketing concerns and is really very
difficult to put a a number on that
would be of value to anybody else
now of course if 20 years have gone by
and for very little money you have
managed to defend your internet facing
app that's doing something highly
sensitive against all you know you've
never had any problems then I would say
okay that's a really good metric good
we've got it but it's that kind of
outcome is very hard to put a number on
the way I'm seeing this now is that the
risk assessment the risk information you
mentioned before actually have a very
important role to play for for this to
decide good
enough because I would imagine that the
risk assessment and risk information at
this point means that part of that comes
from business itself the decisions they
make the tradeoffs they want to make is
that correct indeed and this is a very
business it it depends on the culture of
your business the risk the nature of the
industry you're in personalities of
those involved really this is it's a
very human thing to make these
calls what we can do as
developers is to provide information to
help with those calls so that we're
talking about evidence-based decisions
rather than guesswork so we are already
saying here that to take these decisions
is not simply for the teams alone to the
side on this is really the development
teams talking with the rest of the
business which includes whoever makes
business decisions product managers
maybe small startups could be the CEO
other people to decide how to proceed
how to agree on a good enough definition
that will work for their own context
indeed and I learned this for myself one
of the early teams I worked with as an
as an academic they were very good they
they found all all sorts of whole list
of OSP top 10 problems and they had them
on the backlog and they came to me and
they said Charles you know about
security tell us which ones should we
deal with and I looked at it and I
thought yep that's a product owner
question I have no right you know no
matter how much I know or what my
opinions are I have absolutely no right
to tell a development team how to
prioritize
security that is the product owner's job
why should we settle for just good
enough and not the best we can possibly
get the particular example that comes to
mind the particular story that comes to
mind for this one is something called
the riskmanagement
framework which was invented by the
American
authorities I'm guessing it would have
been perhaps in the '90s
1990s and it was a list of pretty much
all the possible things you could do to
make your Software System
secure and for a long time it was
mandated as
any you know important US Government
project had to satisfy this risk
management framework and eventually they
had to abandon it because the project
had become so
expensive that nobody could afford to
commission
software I I did hear someone muttering
that the abandonment of this was a
communist plot you know it was it was an
enemy thing and I thought no the
Communists would have been delighted at
or the enemy would have been delighted
at the American authorities spending all
that effort doing completely useless
work so that was an example of where
totally good security was just far far
far too expensive there was nothing
wrong with the framework it had lots and
lots of good stuff it was just too
expensive to do as a as a whole with
everything every time so expensive both
I guess in terms of money and time as
well indeed yes and have you got any
examples you can give us from real
projects you worked on where you know
the good enough approach was
followed well the first one that I I was
involved with was the E cach which was
the first mobile money app that that we
worked on and we were novices at
security there was very little
information out there available though
we did consult a couple of Nationwide
experts and but what we particularly did
was a risk assessment with with impact
and probability and based on that we
decided to tackle some of the possible
security threats and not others and we
had an audit Trail and indeed we shared
it with our clients of what we decided
to tackle and what we hadn't and also as
I mentioned earlier the you know what
we'd said was out of scope and you know
might well be the the priority of
another another component in the same
system but in terms of the good enough
approach in a sense it's the almost
every project automatically follows the
well we're not going to do
everything so really what good enough is
talking about is saying well let's be
really selective in this way about which
things we do do and that I've worked on
with several projects recently there was
a lovely one with a piece of software
for government that needed to be really
really really secure it was a kind of
like a riskmanagement framework sort of
piece of software and there was no
question of not doing every single thing
they could to implement
security but what they realized after
doing the analysis was that there was a
time-based element to this and they
could do the the important they could do
the certain things earlier than other
things such that their customers and
here we're talking agile software
development such that their customers
could provide feedback
and understand what was going forward
before the need to pile on all of the
other
detailed security
features so so it's those are two
different kinds of good enough security
it's good enough for now and good enough
forever actually is it even possible to
have something that is good enough
forever in your view you're quite right
of course it isn't it's and indeed an
important part of this as I as I
mentioned earlier is the revisiting this
risk assessment because quite a few
things may change you might get
probability AB ities of things may
change you might have a whole outbreak
of some new sort of attack and you read
about it in your papers and you think oh
we we you know we've upu the likelihood
of that or it might be that your
software is doing or planning to do new
stuff and you've got a range of new
possible threats or possible things that
could go wrong
or you might find just as the sort of
databases expands or the the whole scope
of what you're doing expands you might
find that something that you'd
considered unimportant with a relatively
small number of people has suddenly
become really important so there's lots
of dimensions of of change that could
end up needing a
rethink but the rethink needn't be huge
and involve a lot of people for a long
time this is a matter of we need to
revisit this
might we need to put a different
priority or to start dealing with some
new risks so you gave us an example
where security was really really
important this government project but
are there in general some domains you
can think of for you work with where
good enough means actually quite a lot
I've done a recent project in the health
domain which was a new one to me Health
devices health iot and it was
interesting because yes in a way the
risk was you know the when you're
talking about people's lives yes it's
really really important that things
don't go horribly wrong
but the the approach is very similar
it's just a matter of I say just it's a
matter of deciding which in this
particular context
are the security things and the Privacy
things we need to worry about now moving
on a little bit so in my experience
security and privacy are often treated
as less important than features When
developing a software system yeah nobody
will tell you that everybody will deny
that but this is what I've seen in
practice in many many projects in your
site you say that good security and
privacy are actually important selling
points so can you expand on that yes
they have become so not in every case by
any
means but the archetype I suppose is
Apple take a look at Apple that security
is now their big selling point if you
know they are up against Android what is
what is the reason why Apple really say
you should go for Apple it's because
they Implement in some way better
security so and it's working very well
for them they do get sales because of
that and it really does work there's
another company I've worked with who do
tracking devices for valuable things
that you're shipping around the
world there's a lot of competition for
tracking
devices but if you're shipping a
valuable thing around the world you
probably don't want your adversaries
people who might steal that valuable
to be able to access the information of
exactly where it is now so there
security is an important selling point
it's not just the ability to track that
thing it's the ability to track that
thing without anybody else being able to
know where it is except the people who
should so there's a couple of examples I
find when I've done workshops that
almost every group of develop Vel opers
is able to identify some aspect of the
security or privacy they're implementing
that actually is a potential selling
point what can developers do to convince
decision makers that security and
privacy are important selling points so
you are telling us that they are but we
know as developers that sometimes we say
well these features come first we look
into these other things later on this
often happens so how can we convince
people how can we sell the importance of
security to I don't know product
managers other management other decision
makers in the
company so this requires an important
Insight so I'm going to highlight this
one product owners and people in that
role think in terms of positive selling
points so they are not terribly
interested in bad things that might
happen it's just not in the way of
thinking about it and quite rightly not
so so if you want to make security and
privacy into some kind of selling point
you need a way to turn it around so that
it's positive indeed the very word
security is a classic of this what is
security security is seen as something
positive you know you've got good
Security on your house what does it mean
it's a negative thing nobody can break
in so somebody at some point some
Forerunner of chub or or the locksmiths
or whoever it might have been has
thought yes we're not really selling
people not being able to get in we're
selling security we're selling this
positive
thing so the important thing is not to
try and
sell it in terms of by emphasizing how
bad the bad thing would be one just as a
side observation you know most Senior
Management have got a whole list of the
horrible bad things that might happen
and they just say oh just add it to the
pile we you know we can we we don't
worry about that stuff we just carry on
plowing into the future with thinking
about the good things that might happen
but
if you offer a positive aspect of the
security of what you're
implementing then that becomes something
that a product owner can easily match
against the other things they have to
decide on and I'm certainly not saying
that security should always be or indeed
normally be the first thing those
security
features this is very much a business
decision and it's it'll be different
even with two organizations doing almost
exactly the same product they will take
different decisions but if they are
comparing it as a positive thing against
other positive features they can do that
decision becomes manageable and
sensible and it seems to work quite well
as an
approach so if I understand correctly
what they are saying is try to think
about why you want to do to implement
Security in that way and find something
positive maybe saying your customers
will be more confident in your product
will be easier for them to take the
decision to buy it because the
competitors simply don't offer this nice
aspect something along those lines so
putting well I was about to say a spin
but it's more about uh highlighting the
good things that may
happen if security is implemented in
some
ways yes and the good thing though is as
presented to the potential buyer so
we're not trying to persuade the product
owner that good things will happen we're
giving them a little label a little kind
of advertising slogan that they can then
take to the out side world and best of
all of course if is If the product owner
actually is involved in this creation of
the good thing there was a company I
worked with an excellent company that
was doing a range of different sorts of
websites and they thought about this
they had to do to add security and it
was costing the customers and they they
were sort of the customers were a bit
concerned about this you know can't just
do it why are you charging extra for
this security stuff and and the team
thought about this and thought why don't
we do gold silver and bronze
security then people can see what it is
that they're buying they can match the
level of security against how risky this
particular service this particular web
service is so if somebody says you know
I want to create this high highly
sensitive website that collects very
vital data you can say yep that sounds
good it needs gold security that will
cost you yay much and if they come back
and say no we only want bronze
security you have got something to
discuss with them you know and and that
way of Simply promoting the distinction
and the amount of effort they had to
make was to my mind brilliant I loved it
now when talking about security like any
other system qualities conventional
wisdom tells us that is difficult to
retrofit into software systems sometimes
borderline impossible depending on the
system but when I was doing some
research for this interview I came
across a book called biss scaling
security from a pentester called spark
flow and he says that in situations
where the success of a product or a
service is still in doubt think Young
startup short of cash maybe they don't
have the market fit yet you know they're
trying to find customers and investors
in those situations is better to forget
about security to avoid delays and
potential losses of market
share and as well the associated cost so
he suggest to make the product work fast
so what do you think about this
disposition actually I agree I agree
with spark flow I I think and even if I
didn't I any startup that doesn't do
that is probably not going to get very
far so yes you certainly want to go
ahead without worrying too much about
implementing security and privacy
features but that is not the same as not
thinking about them so I would urge that
same startup to think and do a risk
assessment right at the
beginning and to have that risk
assessment and to know what it is that
they are going to do when the boat comes
in when it's successful when they they
can they've got plenty of money to spend
on it because the thing that is really
difficult to change is the kind of inter
inter faes with the outside world and
the how people use the product and what
it is you're
selling and if
you get that right at the beginning with
just dummy versions of all of the
security stuff you were thinking of
putting in or none at all or so long as
you're aware that you're going to do
this you will make slightly different
decisions than if you just go ahead and
Cobble something together and hope for
the best
also I would suggest that a security
risk assessment is quite a good thing to
give a
funer doesn't cost an enormous amount
and looks good you know yeah they'll all
be aware of the importance of security
and privacy they'll all be worried about
it if you can say yes I know we've not
done it but here's where it goes then
you have got a good story for those
investors so to me it seems that uh your
answer boils down to as long as the
decision is a conscious one and you've
got a plan you'll be fine I always think
of zoom in this context so Zoom as a
relatively unknown company advertised
their security because they had https
connections but they suggested they had
endtoend security which they didn't and
it was only when they were really
successful that I know no they bought up
a company that had that particular
functionality available so they could
offer the story that they'd always had
so to me yes they had good enough
security at all the points it satisfied
we know of problems but none of them
related to the technical technical
intercept ability of it and then when it
was big enough to be a serious threat
they could deal with it
what are the most common mistakes that
software Architects and developers make
when architecting or implementing
Security in their systems I'm thinking
in terms of situations where they end up
with not enough security or maybe too
much so they spend too little or too
much so are there any typical mistakes
that you see people
making my
impression is that the interesting and
the big
problems tend to
be kind of in the
functionality so the simple and
conventional answer to your question is
what are the common mistakes developers
make is go and look at the oasp top 10
list of bad mistakes that developers
make and don't do them
but
actually even the OS top 10 is only of
interest to people with hacking
expertise and there are other errors you
can make and they tend to be related to
functionality where I'm grasping here
for examples but but my general
impression is that errors around
functionality that allow people to make
mistakes or cause data to be shown stuff
to be shown where it shouldn't be shown
or make files available where they
shouldn't be available are the kinds of
mistakes that are actually though not
strictly speaking technical errors they
are actually the most damaging ones and
by far the most common
ones now talking about risk assessment
so in some descriptions of the workshops
you presented at various
conferences you wrote that security and
privacy risk assessment is easy and need
not to take long can you expand on
that I was astonished by
this so I come from an agile background
so my first instinct is to do the
simplest thing that could possibly work
so when I started doing risk assessment
workshops I had in the back of my mind
I'll probably have to teach risk
assessment I have to give examples of
all the things that might go wrong and
and there'd be an awful lot of work
involved but as an experiment I tried
giving a competent team just saying what
could possibly go wrong what are the
risks associated with security and
privacy that could go wrong with this
and to my
surprise
most developers could come up with a
really good set of
problems if they concentrated on just
that I'm not saying it's a complete set
of problems probably not but it was a
very good set of
problems also that didn't really take
very long typically an hour an hour and
a half two hours some went back and did
did a more complete risk assessment on
their own two hours the next
day were're not talking huge Investments
of effort and we're talking a good deal
of learning by the development team as
they do it so a lot of the benefit of
doing this as a group is that everybody
comes away having seen and thought about
what might the problems
be so even though it may come back to
being ultimately to being a product
owner
issue once you've done that risk
assessment everybody is aware of what
could happen and they have a context for
some of those security
discussions and that is tremendously
valuable are there situations for these
assessments where actually having a
security expert would be a must a
must I don't I can't think of any
situation where failing to do it would
be better than doing it without a
security expert and that's no reflection
on Security Experts who are a great you
know that it's great if you can get one
they they're just difficult to get a
hold of similarly we did experiment with
and without product owners as well we
had workshops with and without Security
Experts and we had workshops with and
without product
owners and yes it helps to have a
product owner there they will have a
view on what's Happening they'll
probably be much more aware of of the
likelihood of security problems and the
importance of them because that's the
world they live in but if you don't have
them it's much better to do the workshop
than not or to do let's say to do the
risk assessment than not so my
understanding is that Security Experts
would help but are not indispensable for
this kind of Assessments exactly very
much so we can reach a good enough level
usually
with just the development team and maybe
with a product owner as well better if
the product owner is there but even if
the product owner is not available which
is quite common in many agile teams very
often still these Workshops can give a
very good return on investment in terms
of risk assessments indeed and in terms
of learning for the team yes talking
about cyber security problems so you
claim that they are less likely to Happ
and down cyber Security Experts tend to
suggest and other problems are more
likely so can you expand on that and
also have you got any data to support
this this was mainly based on looking at
the information Commissioner's Office
data so there is astonishingly little
information about how actually
likely cyber problems are there's a
superb survey that surveys a lot of
United Kingdom companies about cyber and
you can get hold of the full data and
analyze it and we've done that so again
from that we can see that although there
are some really nasty cyber companies
have had really nasty cyber problems
actually they're not common at all even
amongst the organizations involved and
the Ico data shows us that what is very
common amongst the the sort of leaks is
things caused really by human error
or humans needing to get on with their
jobs and security getting in the way and
that having some bad outcome so class
things like sharing logins and the like
yeah you have to do it sometimes but it
may have bad
effect and also you talk about using an
industrywide risk model say that to
helps with the discussion what is any
this rewi risk model in this context so
the world is remarkably short of
security and privacy risk models I've
come across one or two there's a recent
nist that's the American department of
security and Analysis of a
it's an embedded device to go in your
body and which is interesting but the
surprisingly little available because
it's usually any kind of risk assessment
is usually seen as company confidential
or organization
confidential so the actual knowledge
that is available
about what are the real problems and
likelihoods for a given
industry is quite small the banks deal
with it by having
informal kind of meetings between the
Security Experts of different banks no
names no pack drill they just they meet
up and they they discuss you know oh I
had lot of problems with that you know
and we're seeing an awful lot of this
and and so they do have a Fab bit of
sharing between the the leading players
there it's not common elsewhere the ncsc
the UK cyber security outfit is sort of
doing their best to pull in more
information but again that only appears
as warnings about new
trends so it is very difficult to find
out what is if you're say in the health
sector what things should you'd be
particularly worried about that so one
thing we we did notice though when we
did this for a particular sector the
health sector was that the numbers
didn't seem to be at the level that
would vary enormously between Industries
so a kind of generic threat model
for applications generally was a great
deal better and more useful than none at
all
that sound right yes let's talk a bit
now about implementing security so let's
start we have a team they want to start
looking to implementing Security in
their into their system what approach
would you suggest them so this is where
we use risk
assessment so it's sometimes called
threat assessment but that suggests
threat modeling is is
is usually used to mean more looking at
existing software and seeing where there
could be problems risk assessment is
looking at the whole system and thinking
why would there be problems and
therefore where would they be and what
do we need to worry about so the classic
way to do risk assessment it's very well
understood in other aspects of Health
standards use it a lot the anybody doing
heavy engineering or you know almost
anything which which has to adopt a
risk-based approach will they may employ
people who do nothing but risk
assessments and risk risk analysis so
this is well-known stuff and you divide
risks into impact and
likelihood so the impact is the range or
the we usually just put a number on it a
ranged to say how bad would it be what
would be the cost in
money lives whatever if this bad thing
happened and the likelihood is well how
often would you expect this to happen
per year if and then that has if we
don't do anything about it and then of
course if we deal with it so you have
the before and after but to start with
we only deal with the before what would
you expect if you don't do anything much
about this the normal way to do that is
you divide into bands and it's low
medium or
high we do suggest that if you're doing
this you have an initial discussion
about what you mean by low medium and
high so put some sort of numbers so that
when people are talking about this is
low this is medium they have an idea
there's a shared understanding of what
that is but the key thing to say about
it is and this has been a surprise to me
is that low medium and high are actually
different orders of magnitude in almost
every
case so typically we find when we're
talking about probability or when we're
talking about impact if we say low or
that might be 10 if we say medium that
might be 100 if we say hi that might be
a
thousand and this is really important
because
it means that when you do a step up
that's 10 times as likely 10 times as
much overall Welly that that risk has so
almost everything else Fades into
insignificance it wouldn't matter if you
had five different lesser ones because
it's still the top one is still by far
the more impactful the more the higher
risk for the organization my
understanding of what you're saying is
basically that when you have the low
medium and high if we go with these
three
levels low is something that
is probably not very well if you're
talking about likelihood not very likely
may happen but it's quite would be quite
unusual if it happened medium is already
something that is quite likely to happen
so say different order of magnitude of
probability here in this case which
means a lot more likely High seems to be
we are we are almost certain that this
will happen so we better do something
about that yeah or or it could be high
as it'll happen to one company in 10
this year that would be a typical high
for a security kind of thing as an
example for in the statistics we've been
using in the Hipster Workshop that's the
latest project I've been working on I
worked out the likelihood of a typical
person getting a burglary or fraud and
the burglary turns out to be about one
in 100 and fraud turns out to be about
one in
10 so fraud is high that's that's high
likelihood burglary is you might say
medium and being struck by lightning is
ultra low you know two or three orders
of magnitude
down and now I'd like to ask you some
recommendations for system so so far I
think what we talked about Works quite
well for Green Field projects we mention
also the fact like startups maybe not
having yet a market Feit so say okay
make the product work first and then
you'll take a care of security or
otherwise you do your assessment involve
the business and decide the boundaries
of where security is important for for
the particular project and get on with
it yeah
but have you got any specific
recommendations for legacy systems where
security was not considered at all in
the original design this
is less common now than it probably was
10 years ago it's an interesting problem
but
ultimately from an engineering
perspective it's the same you still do
the risk assessment you then think about
about what what are the what are the
risks you're dealing with where are you
threatened and then you think about the
mitigations the the things you'll have
to do and change in your existing system
or often put a lay in front to defend it
in order to make that work and after
that it's
engineering the reason I should say why
I why I concentrated on on this kind of
risk assessment and working with working
with product owners is that my
experience has been that software
developers are very good at solving that
kind of problem and I'm a software
developer by background you know if you
say well we've got this problem that we
need to implement this kind of security
or we we don't want the the possible
things coming into the database to be
able to corrupt it using because there's
code in there then a good developer will
find a way of doing doing it there'll be
some some technique or other or you can
look it up or you look it up on the web
or you that will be a way of dealing
with it the important thing is to know
that the problem is there are there any
security measures that you always
recommend for all teams and systems
things that can be done or when be
should be done have very low cost but
potentially a high impact anyway is
there anything like that only risk
assessment so the answer might be it's a
very quick risk assessment don't see any
risks in this but that is the only thing
I would say that is worth doing for
almost any project you know we've talked
about the ones that are small enough not
to worry after that
no but quite often you'll find in terms
of just sheer hygiene you may well find
that keeping the components up to date
is pretty important you might find that
just automatically checking and fixing
bad things in the code which you can get
tools to tell you about that's that
might be
useful but there's very little point in
getting those tools and paying for them
or paying for the effort to install them
if you're not going to actually do
anything with the results and that's not
an unusual outcome
unfortunately or maybe fortunately it
might be that not doing anything about
the problems is again the right decision
this is this is a business tradeoff we
are going back to the risk assessment
again indeed and that's what the risk
assessment's for next question is about
implementing security tasks and
prioritizing them
so how can teams with the tight project
deadlines which as far as I know are
most of the teams out there can actually
prioritize security tasks to implement
without access to Security Experts most
teams don't have this access so for them
could be a bit difficult to decide what
to do first and what is more more
important well again this lies between
the product owners and the development
teams so what
is unusual they're not unique about
security and privacy issues is that
there are functional requirements that
tend to be identified by
developers or certainly technical
people unlike most requirements which
tend to come from the customer so the
the problem as as we've already looked
at that becomes
selling these new things these these new
problems that that have come up and
involving the product owners so that
they know and understand and know why
they're likely to be important to the
customer and using the customer in its
widest possible sense so if it's not
important to the customer I would argue
then that's probably a don't do it but
if it's if it is likely to be um it's so
so we need these two techniques that
we've talked about we need the risk
assessment and we need the turning the
the discoveries round into positive
things for the customer so that the
product owners can make those those
difficult judgments and neither it turns
out and again I'm surprised at this but
it turns out that Security Experts are
not necessary they're useful but they're
not necessary for
either and what is the best approach to
keep security good enough and in line
with the evolution of the system and and
the change in needs of its
users so this is about revisit visiting
the risk assessment
and how often depends entirely on the
nature of your your
project I typically people seem to talk
about every 3 to six months but also you
should be keeping a weather eye on it on
the assessment with each new story or
task you take on to see whether there is
an
implication for security implication for
that task that's already kind of in the
list of threats that you've
got okay I think now I've got some
mandatory questions about AI which is
older age
nowadays in your view has artificial
intelligence the potential of raising
the bar for deciding a good enough
security
level I'd say it doesn't really work
like that so the way it works is good
enough would be related to the current
trends in what's going on so if you read
in the newspapers that that attackers
are using AI to make a certain sort of
attack just automatic and therefore it's
happening to almost everybody instead of
just sort of certain targeted outfits
then you might say all right well we're
going to have to make sure we're not
vulnerable to that one or you might not
it might not matter to you so it becomes
part of the background likelihood of
certain sorts of attacks might well be
changed by the Advent of AI being used
by hostile people yeah he already said
that teams don't necessarily need
Security Experts I mean they are good to
have obviously but they are not
indispensable now we already know that
according to many artificial
intelligence will make developers
redundant According to some in four or
five years
what will happen to Security Experts can
AI replace them as
well I am surprised at the suggestion
that AI will make developers redundant
in four to five
years it will make their jobs different
in one to two years yes redundant I'm
not sure that I see that one very soon
similarly Security Experts yes AI we see
it might make that job a bit easier
indeed there are companies like dark
Trace have been using different sorts of
AI to help address threats for years now
I'm not sure that I can see sort of chat
GPT making a huge amount of difference
to security
because so far as I can find
out the actual amount of knowledge on
the web about this is relatively small
and therefore chat GPT and Bard and the
likes have have really got no
information to play with so you can't
they can't create knowledge that isn't
already there and the knowledge they
create tends to
be at the very least in need of you know
certain checking so I'm not sure that I
can see that sort of AI really helping
very much I mean uh
I could well be wrong I'm
actually interested and concerned about
the possibility of AI use having
security issues and that's you know that
is again going to be part of a whole new
aspect to the risk assessment that is
you will find a great deal in the media
at the moment about you know the
potential hazards with AI use yeah
indeed I guess that that both developers
and Security Experts can relax a bit for
a few more years then I hope you are
right on
this and I think we are at the end of
our interview I think we've done a great
job of introducing this rootless
approach to security for business
developers is there anything that you'd
like to add to mention we should say
that the materials for two different
styles of Workshop are available for
free on the web and that you are very
welcome and please get in touch with me
if you have ideas and suggestions I'd be
delighted thank you Charles I can
confirm that we'll put the links to the
website to the materials in the in the
show notes people I guess can follow you
on Twitter and then how else they can
get in touch with you if you Google
Charles wear Lancaster that'll find
me okay Charles thank you very much for
coming to the show has been a real
pleasure this is joavan proni for
software engineering radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com
you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative comment
license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]